# Manish S. Devana

#### Contact

email: devanamarsci@gmail.com | phone: (413) 281-1989

#### **Research Interests**

I currently study deep ocean circulation in the North Atlantic Program as a PhD student under the Overturning in the Subpolar North Atlantic Program (OSNAP). My research examines abyssal flows across a wide range of physical and temporal scales to understand how flow varies in strength, position, and its hydrographic properties.

## Research Experience

- 1. Time series analysis investigating spatial and temporal variability of ocean currents using moored observations
- 2. Geospatial data analysis using a large range of data types and parameters from satellite derived datasets, lagrangian observations, and model outputs.
- 3. Experience applying ARGO Float data in a range of forms ranging from raw float data to various derived products

## **Fieldwork Experience**

- 1. RAPID-MOCHA Mooring Recovery and Hydrographic Survey Cruise 2018 November
- 2. OSNAP Mooring Mooring Recovery and Hydrographic Survey Cruise 2019 September
- 3. RAPID-MOCHA Mooring Recovery and Hydrographic Survey Cruise 2021 September

### **Publications**

- 1. M. Devana, W.E. Johns (2021): Rapid Freshening of Iceland Scotland Overflow Water Driven by Entrainment of a Major Upper Ocean Salinity Anomaly, *Geophysical Research Letters*
- 2. W.E.Johns, M.Devana, A.Houk, S.Zou (2021): Moored Observations of the Iceland-Scotland Overflow Plume Along the Eastern Flank of the Reykjanes Ridge, *Journal of Geophysical Research: Oceans*

#### **Education**

- 1. 2013-2015 New York University, Biochemistry
- 2. 2015-2018 University of Southamption, UK, Physical Oceanography MSCi (integrated BSC & MSC)
- 3. 2018-Present (expected June 2023) University of Miami, Meteorology and Physical Oceanography PhD

#### **Technical Skills**

#### Coding

- 1. Python (Strong)
  - Experience using geospatial datasets with core earth science python packages (xarray,cartopy, dash, GMT, netcdf, numpy, scipy)
  - Developed python programs for oceanographic field work (CTD and mooring data processing, mooring trilateration, instrument calibrations)
  - Extensive experience with time series analysis
  - Open science oriented methods
- 2. Julia (Proficient)
  - o Experience with numerical fluid dynamics simulations, gesopatial and time series data analysis
- 3. Matlab (Strong)
- 4. Javascript (Proficient)

## **Professional Development**

- 1. Graduate Undergraduate Mentoring (GUM) Co-Founder and Mentor (2020-2023)
- 2. COMPASS Student Seminar Series Speaker (2019, 2020, 2021)
- 3. University of Miami Teaching Assistant Intro to Marine Science Lab (Fall 2019)
- 4. University of Miami Teaching Assistant Python Programming for Marine Science (Fall 2021)

#### **Awards**

- 1. 2019 Outstanding Student Presentation Award AGU Fall Meeting 2019
- 2. COMPASS Student Seminar Series Best Graphics 2019-20
- 3. COMPASS Student Seminar Series 3rd Place Overall 2021-22

# **Other Work Experience**

- 1. Wetlab Bar Bartender (2019-present)
- 2. University of Southampton Student Union Event Staff and Bartender (2016-2018)

### References

- Wiliam E. Johns: Professor, Meteorology and Physical Oceanography, University of Miami, RSMAS
- Mohamed iskandarani: Professor, Meteorology and Physical Oceanography, University of Miami, RSMAS